[MUSIC]
[음악]
So the normalized count vectors that we just described helped address some
정규화된 단어수 벡터는 최초 구상대로
of the issues with our original proposal of just using raw
단어수만을 통해 문서를 나타낼 시
word counts as our representation of the document.
발생하는 문제 해결에 도움이 됐습니다
But there's another issue, which is often what we'd like to do is really
다른 안건도 있는데
emphasize the important words in a document.
문서의 주요 단어 강조입니다
So we're gonna discuss a little bit about what it means to be an important word and
주요 단어가 뭔지 설명하고
how we can think about emphasizing them.
어떻게 강조할지 고민해봅시다
Okay, before we talk about important words, let's first talk about rare words.
주요 단어를 논하기 전에 희소 단어부터 봅시다
So again, let's imagine that we're reading an article about soccer, and
또다시 축구에 관한 기사를 읽는데
in this article there are lots and lots of common words like the and
선수, 경기장, 골과 같은 상용어가
player and field and goal.
많이 등장한다고 합시다
And what we mean by a common word,
상용어란
it's a word that appears frequently in the corpus.
말뭉치에 자주 등장하는 단어를 뜻합니다
In the corpus, that's just terminology for all the documents out there
말뭉치란 검색 작업 시 대상이 되는
that we are looking at when we're doing this task of retrieval.
모든 문서의 합을 뜻하는 용어로
And what happens though is that these common words dominate the similarity
말뭉치에서 문서들 간 비교시 이런 상용어가
metric that we talked about when we compare against other documents because,
유사도 기준을 크게 좌우하게 되는데
like I said, these words appear in lots and lots of documents.
이 단어들은 많은 문서에서 나타나기 때문입니다
Whereas in contrast,
그에 반해
there are some very rare words in this document we're looking at.
희소 단어들도 있습니다
Words like "futbol" and "Messi", the specific player we're reading about,
futbol, Messi와 같은 단어들은
that get completely swamped by all these common words.
상용어에 의해 묻혀버립니다
they get swamped because they just appear very infrequently in the corpus.
말뭉치에 적게 등장하기 때문에 묻혀버리죠
So let's think about how to increase the importance of these rare words,
이런 희소 단어들의 중요도를 높일 방법을 연구해볼 텐데
because those often are the ones that are really relevant in describing what's
이런 단어들이 기사의 특징을 잘 잡아내며
unique about this article, and what might indicate which other articles out there,
카를로스는 그런 기사들을
Carlos for example, is interested in reading.
읽고 싶어할 것이기 때문입니다
Okay, so like we said, what characterizes a rare word is the fact
희소 단어는 말뭉치에서
that it infrequently appears in the corpus and
희귀하게 등장하는 단어라 할 수 있는데
what we wanna do is we somehow wanna up-weight these rare words and
이런 희소 단어들의 가중치를 어떻게든 높여서
equivalently to thinking about emphasizing words that only appear in a few documents,
적은 수의 문서에만 등장하는 단어를 강조하고
we can think about taking each word and discounting the weight on that
각 단어의 가중치를
word based on how many documents that word appears in in the entire corpus.
말뭉치 전체 등장빈도에 기반해 낮춥니다
Okay, so a question is, do we really want to just emphasize the rare words?
그러면 정말 희소 단어를 강조해야 할까요?
Well, we clearly don't want to emphasize the very common words,
당연히 상용어를 강조하고 싶진 않은데
the words like the and a and it and everything like that.
the, a, it 같은 단어입니다
But what we wanna include are things that are very relevant for that document.
하지만 문서에 관련되어 있다면 포함시켜야 합니다
So not just words like Messi, but also probably soccer and field and goal.
메시뿐만 아니라 축구, 경기장, 골 같은 단어입니다
Things that describe the sport that we're looking at,
이런 단어는 주제로 삼는 스포츠를 묘사하지만
which might be different than even another article about sports.
다른 스포츠 기사와는 다를 수 있습니다
An article about basketball that talks about basketball
농구 기사는 농구대, 코트 같은
hoop and court and words like that.
단어가 나오겠죠
So in this case, we wanna emphasize what I'll call important words.
주요 단어만을 강조하고 싶습니다
Okay?
알겠죠?
And so what we're gonna trade off here is we're gonna think about
문서에 무척 자주 등장하면
Words that appear very frequently in the document so
읽고 있는 문서와 관련이 있는 건지
they're relevant to the document that we're currently reading.
균형을 생각해야 합니다
So I'll call this common locally.
이걸 들어 국소적으로 흔하다고 말합니다
And at the same time we want them to appear relatively infrequently in
그와 동시에 말뭉치에서 상대적으로 드물기를 바라는데
the corpus so I'll call this rare globally and what characterizes a quote unquote
이걸 전역적으로 희귀하다고 말하고 주요 단어를
important word Is some trade off between this local frequency, and global rarity.
결정짓는 건 국소적 빈도와 전역적 희귀성 간의 균형입니다
[MUSIC]
[음악]